Yeah.
Good morning. We have you here to speak about the Modern Slavery Bill.
Citizens Advice Bureau. Just acknowledging we'll all have
your services in our community, so just appreciate that in advance.
And also acknowledging thank you for working with us around the report
so that you're able to speak in public.
Think it's for the best of all those involved that this is a public hearing.
So, with that, we have 10 minutes with you.
We would always like time for questions, so just factor that into your
contribution, and we'll hand it over to you.
Yeah. Kia ora.
I am Gwyneth Carey-Smith, and I'd just like to introduce my colleagues,
Andrew Hubbard, deputy CE, and
Louise May, our national social policy advisor.
Yeah, so we would like to support our submit to the committee,
our Citizen Advice Bureau spotlight report on migrant worker
exploitation in Aotearoa, New Zealand.
Kia manaaki i te mana mānene.
Which hopefully you've all got a copy of.
If you don't, I can just pass you one.
So the report was first initiated by CAB's telling us
that they were seeing an increase in migrants experiencing working
exploitation despite changes like the introduction of the
accredited employer work visa, which had actually been introduced to
help reduce exploitation by allowing only good quality
employers to employ migrants. CAB's also expressed
concern about there being limited pathways and no support for
people to move out of harm when on temporary work visas, even when
their human rights were breached in this country.
The report is framed by the principle manaaki i te
tangata, caring for people, upholding their mana, and recognizing the
dignity and rights of everyone who lives and works here.
And I'm sure that's a principle that we all ascribe to.
As you will see, the case studies tell the stories of migrants who are
experiencing exploitation and their efforts to access justice and
safety in Aotearoa, New Zealand. These stories are anonymized, but they are
true accounts, so I really encourage you to read them.
We know that this report will be of value to you as you share our concern about the
amount of exploitation that is occurring in our country.
The report shows that exploitation is happening across locations,
businesses, industries, and job positions.
It's grounded in the inquiries that we received over a
two-year period,
until May 2026, and that's about 1,000 inquiries
analyzed. And we know that this is an under-representation of the
number of people in exploitative situations.
So from this report, we can learn about who's affected by migrant worker
exploitation in Aotearoa, New Zealand, what harm is occurring, and how we can
act on what needs to change.
And so as we've previously said, like, we recognize that this bill
is a major step forward for New Zealand.
Our concern is that there's a lot more that needs to be done based on what we're
seeing in our communities. For example, ending tied visas
and the things that could be included and implemented in this bill, such as
removing the revenue threshold, installing support for affected people,
adding due diligence, and establishing an independent anti-slavery commissioner.
So we can encourage you to consider the list of actionable insights in the
report
for greater understanding of what needs to change.
There are things like redesigning the migrant exploitation protection visa to
include others impacted by exploitation who aren't on the
accredited employer work visa, renaming the visa, and extending its
timeframe.
So the Modern Slavery Bill needs to be effective for addressing slavery, not only
within industries and businesses offshore, but also those
onshore in our country. So our concern is that the current
threshold criteria removes responsibility from small and medium businesses
to comply with this law, and yet it's at this scale of
industry that we see much of the harm being inflicted on people in our country.
Subcontractors and other third-party operators need to be
accountable for upholding labor rights that are ascribed to in the broader
contracts.
The report shows that people need support when moving out of situations
of harm, and yet this bill is proposing to delay this requirement.
Our report clearly shows that support for people experiencing exploitation in
this country is insufficient and much overdue,
and we are creating more harm to people that we have invited to work here,
that we rely on working here, and that we have approved to work here by
not supporting any of their needs if they are exploited.
The basic needs such as food, shelter, legal support, and
healthcare.
So as we've already submitted on this bill, supporting and asking for improvements
to the proposed legislation, we'd like to use the rest of the time to answer any
questions about our report, and our insights from the CAB
into migrant worker exploitation here in Aotearoa, New Zealand.
Wonderful. Thank you very much. We have a question from Phil Twyford.
Like Katie, I just wanted to say thank you for the work that you do.
I know probably in all of our communities, but ones that I represent,
CAB's very active and, yeah, plays a very positive role.
Can you talk a bit about one of the actionable insights in the report is
this idea of decoupling the visa from the
employer.
Can you talk about why you think that's a
good idea?
I'll pass that to Louise for that.
It's really common for clients to tell us that they feel
trapped by being in a visa of that kind.
It's regularly being used by employers
to keep people in situations that are
exploitative or abusive.
They're threatening using that visa as a basis for
the threats. It's really, really common for people who are coming in
under the accredited employee work visa scheme, to tell us that.
Mm.
So, we see it as
a major source of the power imbalance
Between the employee and the employer that is
facilitating some of the exploitative and abusive behavior that's
happening.
And we've actually had a client tell us
that the tied visa makes her feel like she's
in bondage, she's in a kind of slavery type situation.
Yeah.
So, yeah, we do see it as a really key move that government could
take to address the exploitation that is
occurring by empowering people to feel
more able to move out of those exploitative situations
because putting the technicalities of how it all works aside, it's the
way that it makes the workers feel trapped and feel
unable to move. It's a disincentive for them to
explore avenues for getting out.
Thank you. I have another one, Katie, but do you want to share?
Yeah. Oh, we'll go to Camilla, and then we'll come back.
I think Tiano's got a question.
Oh. No, go.
Okay. Yep, we'll share it around.
So just a thank you for this report, and I share some of your
concerns around what happens for people who are experiencing modern
slavery conditions in New Zealand at the moment.
What would you say would be the one most impactful thing
that Parliament could do to try and address the situation for
people who are in New Zealand?
Well,
just adding to what Louise said with the visa being tied,
what we're seeing is that people are in places of extreme hardship.
They haven't been paid. They have-
Mm
... sometimes their accommodation, even though it's hideous, is associated with
their employment. The fact that there is no support for people to move out of
harm, that would make a big difference for people to be able
to move out of exploitative situations and also-
Mm
... be able to report. Even have some confidence in
reporting where they're at because they know that they'll be protected.
Yeah. Is that-
Yeah, I just really want to bolster what Gwynn has said.
It's one thing to have a migrant exploitation protection visa
available to people, but it's an entire other thing to be able to
survive when you're no longer in that situation.
So the question of income for people and social
supports is critical.
Yeah. Our CAB volunteers are genuinely horrified and shocked
when people come to them and there is nothing available to support them.
They've not been paid, they can't pay the rent, they can't afford food, and
yet they're not eligible for any kind of support despite clearly being a victim of
exploitation. And our volunteers are having to
send them to food banks, look at what could possibly do, and asking them whether
they can borrow money from friends and family.
And these are victims of exploitation.
Our volunteers are absolutely shocked that that's the situation that people are
being put in.
Mm.
Can I ask you something on that?
Yes. Yeah, go for it.
So do you have a
proposal or an idea about how to address that problem of people
losing employment for whatever reason, and suddenly they've got no means of
support? What do you think should be done?
I think people need to be eligible for some kind of income support
assistance for a period of time after they've experienced a situation like
that-
Yeah
... so that they can feed themselves and find somewhere to live.
Yeah.
I don't think we can really avoid looking at that
if we are serious about addressing the situation and the impacts of it on people.
Thank you. Tiano, for you.
Yeah. I was just looking at one of your insights here, and I agree with what you're
saying. I think decoupling those visas would be a good move.
This part around stronger enforcement of employment law, do you have
any specific laws in
particular that you think we should be focusing on as a
parliament? And then any examples which you have
that
would show that that would be a good thing in terms of changing?
I think this recommendation speaks to our wider
experience of employment situations.
We've had a really significant increase in employment inquiries over the last 10
years,
where we see
many situations where the law is clearly being breached.
It's not
a is it or isn't it. People aren't being paid the minimum wage.
People are being exploited in a whole variety of ways, whether they're
migrants or New Zealand workers.
And we're really concerned about the lack of enforcement of the law and
the challenges that employees have in those situations when they're
dependent on these jobs and so therefore unwilling to take ...
It makes it really hard for them to take action.
So the migrant exploitation is an exacerbation of that
because those migrants who might be just on a visa status are even more
powerless in those situations. But as a symptom of a larger issue that we're seeing
across the employment space.
And a final question from Pamchet. Pamela.
Yeah. Thank you so much. Mine is also about one of your actionable insights.
This is about improving safe reporting pathways.
So what is unsafe at the moment? Can you elaborate on this for me?
It was interesting, a feedback we had from our CABs is the
demographics that we have from our inquiries.
They pointed to
the organized crime that happens in some of those countries that
people come from. And Imbie noted
that even when trying to investigate some of these
situations, that people
will
bail out halfway through that investigation.
And some of that's being paid off, being threatened.
And I think that's part of understanding
the extreme fear that people are in and
threats to their safety.
So
protection,
it has to relate to the person themselves, what's going on for them, but
understanding that there are physical threats to
both them and their family onshore from
offshore-
Yeah. It's non-pleasant.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, I've just read an example this morning where a person was requesting
their passport to be returned to them.
So then they got physically assaulted, their phone taken off them.
It's not easy for people to move out of these situations.
Mm-hmm.
And they need to be supported, and they need to be protected.
I think the other aspect of that as well is that, in terms of trying to
resolve issues, there's no separate pathway for-
Mm
... for migrants facing exploitation.
They still are using the same mechanisms that any employment
dispute would use. And so we see sometimes these exploited migrants
being
put into mediation with their exploitative worker-
Mm-hmm
... as the pathway to resolution. And
that's often re-traumatizing for the person who's been
exploited. And yet, there's no specific pathway that says, well,
that's probably not appropriate in those situations.
Can I just say thank you very much. We have reached the end of our time, but I've
just got to say that obviously the work you do, just to back that up again, but
also the passion to bring this to us.
While the scope of this bill may not necessarily be the solution to some
of this, I know you've inspired, well, I speak on behalf of everyone, it
definitely inspired me to think about how we can treat that in some other
ways. So,
I know that you'll hopefully see some responses, no doubt, from people, so
appreciate it. Thank you for your time. Thank you for the report.
Thank you so much.
Does anybody else need a copy, or?
No, we've got one.
We have a copy.
We have one, yeah.
I wouldn't mind a paper copy if it's-- Sure.
Awesome.